<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "./dtd/faq-v10.dtd">

<faqs title="Frequently Asked Questions">

<faq title="General">
    <question>What is Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        The goal of the Batik project is to provide a framework for Java language applications 
        which manipulate SVG content for various purposes, such as generation, manipulation or viewing. 
        The project's ambition is to give the developer a set of core modules which can be used together 
        or individually to support specific SVG solutions. Examples of modules are SVG parsers, SVG 
        generators and SVG DOM implementations. Even though the goal of the project is to provide a set 
        of core modules, one of the delivery is a full fledged SVG Viewer implementation which 
        validates the various modules and their inter-operability. 
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>Where does the name come from?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        <!-- Will include description from Patrick Megard, who initially proposed the name -->
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How did it start?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik started out because several teams doing SVG related projects decided to join 
        efforts with the idea that the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts. The
        following companies or institutions are part of the team that contributed and 
        created the initial Batik project:
        <ul>
            <li><link href="http://www.csiro.au/">CSIRO</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.ilog.fr/">ILOG</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/koala/jackaroo/">Jackaroo</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.kodak.com/">Eastman Kodak Company</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.sun.com">Sun Microsystems, Inc.</link></li>
        </ul>
        In addition, the Batik project is supported by <link href="http://www.ibm.com">IBM</link>.
        </p>
        <p>
        This is a lot of big companies: is Batik only for big companies? Certainly not!
        Even though some big companies are involved in Batik, the project is not limited
        to big corporations and, as all other Apache project, is opened to everyone based
        on merit.
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How can I contribute?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        The process for contributing to Batik is the same as for other Java projects 
        at Apache. For example, a formal description of that process can be found on the 
        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/guidelines/index.html">Jakarta</link> web
        site.
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>What can I do with Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Discuss what can be done now and some possible future plans.
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>Where can I find the SVG specification?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How can I create and author SVG content?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>What are the benefits of SVG being an XML grammar?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How can I see a demo?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>What other SVG products are out there?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>Why do we have such a project at Apache?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How does Batik relate to other Apache projects?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Talk about FOP and Cocoon.
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>What is coming next?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Depends on contributions and feedback.
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How much of SVG does Batik implement?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq title="Developers">
    <question>What are the System Requirements to run Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How do I install Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>Which JDK version do I need?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>

    <question>How do I submit patches or bug fixes?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        </p>
    </answer>


</faq>
</faqs>