<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

   Copyright 2000-2004  The Apache Software Foundation 

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- author vincent.hardy@eng.sun.com                                       -->
<!-- author cjolif@ilog.fr                                                  -->
<!-- version $Id$ -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "./dtd/faq-v10.dtd">

<faqs title="Frequently Asked Questions">

<faq>
    <question>What is Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>        <img src="images/batikUses.jpg" alt="Batik use cases" />
        Batik is a Java(tm) technology
        based toolkit for applications or applets that want to use images in the
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/">Scalable Vector
        Graphics (SVG)</link> format for various purposes, such as
        viewing, generation or manipulation.        
        </p>
        <p>
        It is the ambition of this project to give developers a set of
        <link href="architecture.html">core modules</link> which can
        be used together or individually to support specific SVG
        solutions. Examples of modules are an <link
        href="glossary.html#SVGParser">SVG parser</link>, an <link
        href="glossary.html#SVGGenerator">SVG generator</link> and an
        <link href="glossary.html#SVGDOM">SVG DOM </link>
        implementations. Another ambition of the Batik project is to
        make it highly extensible (for example, Batik allows the
        developer to handle <link href="extendingBatik.html">custom
        SVG tags</link>).  Even though the goal of the project is to
        provide a set of core modules, one of the deliveries is a full
        fledged <link href="svgviewer.html">SVG Browser</link>
        implementation which validates the various modules and their
        inter-operability.
        </p>
        <p>
        Batik provides <link href="architecture.html">building
        blocks</link> that developers can assemble in various ways in
        their Java technology applications or applets to generate,
        parse, view or convert SVG contents. For example, Batik
        contains a Swing component that can add <link
        href="svggen.html">SVG viewing capability</link> to all Java
        technology applications or applets. Batik can also be used to
        generate SVG on a client or on a server, and Batik can <link
        href="svgrasterizer.html">convert SVG content</link> into
        other formats such as JPEG, PNG or Tiff or other formats
        (<link href="rasterizerTutorial.html"> transcoder API</link>).
        Batik's goal is to make it easy for developers to handle SVG
        content for many purposes, client-side or server-side, as
        illustrated in the diagram.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What is SVG?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/">SVG</link> (Scalable Vector Graphics) is an open-standard language for describing 
        two-dimensional (2D) graphics in XML. It is a Recommendation from the 
        <link href="http://www.w3.org">W3C</link>. SVG lets you describe rich images
        with features such as gradients, transparency, filter effects and animation.
        </p>
        <p>
        SVG has three types of graphic objects: shapes (e.g., paths consisting 
        of straight lines and curves), images and text. Graphical objects can be grouped, 
        styled, transformed and composited (e.g., drawn with transparency). SVG has a 
        large set of static features which includes nested transformations, clipping 
        paths, masking and filter effects.
        </p>
        <p>
        In addition, SVG images can be dynamic and interactive. A rich set of event
        handlers such as 'onmouseover' and 'onclick' can be assigned to any SVG
        graphical object. These handlers can invoke scripts, which, in response to an
        event, can dynamically modify the SVG graphic through the SVG Document Object Model
        (DOM) API, allowing, for example scripts to change the color or location of graphical 
        elements in reaction to events. </p>
        <p>SVG graphical elements can be animated through scripting. Alternatively,
        animation sequences can be expressed directly in XML because SVG leverages the
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/">SMIL</link> specification for multimedia,
        another <link href="http://www.w3.org">W3C</link> specification. 
        </p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What can I do with Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik contains several <link href="architecture.html">core modules</link> which can be used independently or jointly to 
        <strong>generate SVG content</strong> (see the <link href="svggen.html">SVG Generator</link>, an 
        <link href="domapi.html">SVG DOM</link> implementation documentation)
        <strong>view SVG content</strong> (see the <link href="jsvgcanvas.html">JSVGCanvas</link>)
        or <strong>convert to and from the SVG format</strong> (see the 
        <link href="rasterizerTutorial.html">SVG Transcoders</link> tutorial).
        </p>
        
        <p>
        In addition, Batik contains <link href="architecture.html#lowLevelComponents">low level modules</link> such as
        an object oriented Graphic Vector Toolkit (<link href="glossary.html#GVT">GVT</link>),
        a set of low level parsers(<link href="glossary.html#SVGParser">SVG Parser</link>) specific to the SVG syntax and
        a set of <link href="extendingBatik.html">extensions</link> to the Java 2D API (such as sophisticated fill types and 
        filter effects).
        </p>

        <p>
        Finally, Batik comes with <link href="toolsAndApps.html">packaged applications</link> to help developers get
        familiar with the code and be quickly able to use the various modules: an 
        <link href="svgviewer.html">Squiggle</link> (in the 
        <code>org.apache.batik.apps.svgbrowser</code> package) an 
        <link href="svgrasterizer.html">SVG rasterizer</link> (in the 
        <code>org.apache.batik.apps.rasterizer</code> package), a
        <link href="ttf2svg.html">Font converter</link> (in the
        <code>org.apache.batik.apps.ttf2svg package</code>) and an 
        <link href="svgpp.html">SVG pretty printer</link> (in the 
        <code>org.apache.batik.apps.svgpp package</code>).</p>
        <p>
        <strong>Squiggle</strong> the SVG browser <link
        href="svgviewer.html">(here)</link> can display SVG documents
        and lets the user zoom, pan and rotate any SVG document, view
        the SVG source, link between SVG documents, view a tree
        representation of the SVG DOM and more. One important
        component of the SVG viewer is the
        <code>org.apache.batik.swing.JSVGCanvas</code> component which
        can be plugged in any Java application or applet to provide
        SVG viewing capability.
        </p>
        <p>
        The <strong>SVG rasterizer</strong> <link
        href="svgrasterizer.html">(here)</link> lets the user convert
        SVG files to raster formats such as JPEG, PNG or Tiff . It
        contains an extensible mechanism so that arbitrary raster
        formats can be added. For example, the rasterizer lets you
        create one SVG file with a special effect (e.g., shadows,
        gradients, etc...), turn it into an PNG image, then modify the
        SVG source (e.g., modify a piece of text or a color), and
        generate another PNG image from it. This way, you can easily
        generate a series of images sharing a common theme or look and
        feel to post on a web site (note that the rasterizer can also
        be used on a web server to do this conversion automatically).
        </p>
        <p>
        The <strong>SVG Font Converter</strong><link
        href="ttf2svg.html">(here)</link> lets the user easily create
        an <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/fonts.html">SVG
        Font</link> for a set of characters from a True Type Font
        file. That SVG Font definition can be embedded in a document
        using the characters. This allows users to create SVG
        documents that are self contained and do not rely on system
        fonts, and guarantees that the SVG file will be displayed
        exactly as it was authored on all platforms.
        </p>

        <p>
        The <strong>SVG Pretty Printer</strong><link
        href="svgpp.html">(here)</link> is a convenience tool to
        pretty print an SVG document, which means that you can
        reformat any existing SVG document to produce a properly
        formatted and highly legible version.</p>

        <!-- <p>The SVG Generator (in the
        <code>org.apache.batik.util.awt.svg</code> package) that
        allows all Java applications or applets to export their
        graphics to the SVG format.
        
        The SVG generator lets all Java application or applets export
        their graphics as SVG, using the same code used for drawing to
        the screen or for printing. For example, an application that
        displays a pie chart in a window, can use the SVG generator to
        easily export the sequence of Java2D drawing calls for the pie
        chart to a SVG format.
        </p>
        -->

        <p>
        These applications show that Batik can be used client side
        (the browser can be used on any client machine) and server
        side (the rasterizer can be used to serve SVG images to client
        machines that do not have SVG support).
        </p>
        <p>
        <link href="svgviewer.html">Squiggle</link> the SVG browser and the
        <link href="svgrasterizer.html">rasterizer</link> are examples
        of some of the types of applications Batik allows. Batik's
        <link href="architecture.html">architecture</link> allows the
        modules to be used in many different ways so other
        applications are possible, such as using the <link
        href="rasterizerTutorial.html">transcoders</link> (to other
        vector formats, such as PDF, for example). Furthermore, the
        <link href="glossary.html">Graphic Vector Toolkit</link> could
        be used to render other graphic formats such as <link
        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">XHTML</link>.
        </p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How can I see a demo?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        You can see an online demonstration of Squiggle the SVG
        browser on the <link href="batikDemo.html">demo
        page</link>. Alternatively, you can <link
        href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/xml/batik">download</link>
        Batik or see <link href="svgviewer.html">screenshots</link> of
        the Batik SVG viewer, images created from the <link
        href="svgrasterizer.html">rasterizer</link> and an <link
        href="svggen.html">example</link> of how to use the <link
        href="svggen.html">SVGGraphics2D</link> generator.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>Why do we have such a project at Apache?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/mission.html">Apache's
        mission</link> is to allow the web to be an open environment
        and to remain an open environment. Batik as an open source
        implementation of a key format for today's and tomorrow's web
        fits well in this mission.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How does Batik relate to other Apache projects?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik is used in <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/index.html">Cocoon</link> 
        for server side rasterization of SVG images. In addition, the Batik is used in the 
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/fop/index.html">FOP</link> project to convert 
        SVG images to PDF format.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How did it start?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik started out because several teams doing SVG related projects decided to join 
        efforts with the idea that the whole will be greater than the sum of the parts. The
        following companies or institutions are part of the team that contributed and/or
        created the initial Batik project, during the fall of 2000:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><link href="http://www.csiro.au/">CSIRO</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.ilog.com/">ILOG</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://koala.ilog.fr/">Koala Team</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.kodak.com/">Eastman Kodak Company</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://www.sun.com">Sun Microsystems, Inc.</link></li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        In addition, the Batik project is supported by <link href="http://www.ibm.com">IBM</link>.
        </p>
        <p>
        We encourage anyone to participate. As with all ASF project, all efforts are
        volunteer-based. We are looking for individuals to work with us on
        fulfilling our goals for Batik in the spirit of collaborative open-source
        software development.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How can I contribute?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        The Batik Project is an open volunteer project in the 
        spirit of the <link href="http://www.apache.org">Apache
        Software Foundation</link> (ASF).  This means that there are
        many ways to contribute to the project, either with direct
        participation (coding, documenting, answering questions,
        proposing ideas, reporting bugs, suggesting bug-fixes, etc..)
        or by resource donation (publicity, hardware, software,
        conference presentations, speeches, etc...). Applications that
        use the Batik modules, such as tools or extensions, are of special 
        interest to the project.
        </p>
        <p>
        The process for contributing to Batik is the same as for other
        Java projects at Apache. A formal description of that process
        can be found on the <link
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/guidelines/index.html">Jakarta</link>
        web site.(<link href="whoAreWe.html#BatikCommitters">Batik Commiters</link> and 
        <link href="whoAreWe.html#BatikContributors">Batik Contributors</link>)
        </p>
        <p>
        For direct participation, we suggest you to subscribe to the
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">Batik mailing
        list</link> (follow the link for information on how to
        subscribe and to access the mail list archives), and to
        checkout the <link
        href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/xml-batik/">latest
        code</link>.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>Where is Batik going? What is next?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>The SVG implementation is not complete <link
        href="status.html">(status)</link>, and there is more work to
        do to achieve a fully functional viewer.</p>

        <p>Batik 1.1 supports all the <link
        href="status.html#beSuiteStatus">static SVG features</link>,
        linking and a limited support for <link
        href="scripting.html">scripting</link>. Work has started on
        <link href="status.html#DynamicTest">dynamic
        features</link>. Scripting support with the 1.5 beta releases,
        and declarative animation (known as SMIL animation) will be
        supported in the 2.0 release.
        </p>
        <p>The type of applications (e.g., transcoding applications)
        that can or will be added to Batik depends on contributions
        and feedback.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How can I create and author SVG content?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Well, you can always use a plain text editor such as vi or
        xemacs, but there are many graphic authoring packages that can
        export SVG documents and that will let you author SVG content
        visually.
        </p>
        <p>
        You can get a list of tools exporting SVG from the <link
        href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/SVG-Implementations#edit">SVG
        implementation</link> section of the SVG Home page on the W3C
        web site. You can also imagine building a tool on top of
        Batik: feel free to contribute!
        </p>
        <p>
        Authoring is one way of creating SVG content, and graphic
        authoring packages are useful for that purpose. However, there
        are many types of graphics which can be generated, such as
        stock quotes, statistical data, etc. For these types of
        graphics, there are many ways to generate SVG content. For
        example, if your data (say stock information) is contained in
        an XML document, you could use XSLT to transform your XML data
        into SVG. If your data comes from a database and you retrieve
        that data in a servlet on a Web server (e.g., using JDBC), you
        could use the Java binding for the DOM API to generate an SVG
        document from the data base data. You could also use Batik's
        SVG generator and use the Java 2D API to generate that
        graphic.
        </p>
        <p>
        The following URLs will be useful to learn more about each of 
        these solutions:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><link href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/index.html">Xalan for XSLT</link></li>
            <li><link href="http://xml.apache.org/xerces-j/index.html">Xerces</link> and
                <link href="http://java.sun.com/xml/download.html">Crimson</link> for the DOM API</li>
            <li><link href="svggen.html">SVG Generator</link></li>
        </ul>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What other SVG products are out there?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        There are many companies supporting SVG and you will find a list of 
        available implementations on the <link href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/SVG-Implementations">
        W3C's SVG implementation page</link>
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>

    <question>Where can I find the SVG specification?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        The SVG specification is available from the 
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/">W3C Web site</link> 
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How much of SVG does Batik implement?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        The following <link href="status.html">status page</link>
        shows how much of the SVG specification Batik implements by
        showing which of the tests in the <link
        href="status.html#beSuiteStatus">SVG Basic Effectivity test
        suite</link> Batik successfully passes.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What are the benefits of SVG being an XML grammar?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Being an XML grammar means SVG can leverage work done around
        XML, and SVG actually leverages other grammars such as <link
        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-xlink-20010627/">XLink</link>,
        for linking and <link
        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-smil-animation-20010904/#AnimationFramework">SMIL</link>
        for the animation.
        </p>
        <p>
        Beyond the use and mix with other XML syntaxes, being an XML grammar
        lets SVG benefit from the plethora of XML tools that make it so easy
        to manipulate, generate, search and edit SVG files.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>


<faq>
    <question>Where does the name come from?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik is a highly evolved art tradition that developed in Java
        (one of the islands comprising what is now called
        Indonesia). Batik is generally thought of as the quintessentially
        Indonesian textile. Motifs of flowers, twining plants, leaves,
        buds, birds, butterflies, fish, insects and geometric forms are
        rich in symbolic association and variety; there are about three
        thousand recorded batik patterns.
        </p>
        <p>
        We think that Batik gracefully evokes Java, graphics and
        high-quality, terms that constitute the core of the toolkit.
        </p>
        <p>
        The following <link href="http://www.culturalbridge.com/idgallbk1.htm">
        page</link> shows examples of what Batik textures look like.</p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What are the System Requirements to run Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        Batik is written in the Java language and requires a version 1.3
        implementation at this time. 
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How do I install Batik?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        You will need the <link href="http://java.sun.com/">JDK
        1.3</link> to run Batik.
        </p>
        <p>
        To install Batik you need to <link href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/xml/batik">download</link>
        the binary or source distribution and unzip it on your computer.
        </p>
	<p>You can have a look at the <link
	href="install.html">installation instructions</link> for more
	information.
	</p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>How do I submit patches or bug fixes?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        You can submit bug fixes and patches to the <link
        href="mailto:batik-dev@xml.apache.org">Batik developers</link>
        mailing list and you can enter bugs in <link
        href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla</link>.
        </p>
    </answer>

</faq>

<faq>
    <question>What scripting languages can I use in my SVG files?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>
        A limited support of scripting in SVG files is provided with
        the current version of Batik (script are executed but dynamic
        update is not supported).
    	</p>
	    <p>
	    Batik can recognize the following scripting languages:
	    </p>
	    <ul>
	        <li>ECMAScript thanks to the <link
	        href="http://www.mozilla.org/rhino">Mozilla
	        Rhino</link> JavaScript engine included in the
	        distribution.
	        </li>
	        <li>Python for which you need to download the <link
	        href="http://www.jython.org">Jython</link> engine.
	        </li>
	        <li>Tcl for which you need to download the <link
	        href="http://dev.scriptics.com/software/java/">Jacl</link>
	        engine.
	        </li>
	    </ul>
	    <p>
	    To get more information on how to install optional
	    scripting languages you can have a look at the <link
	    href="install.html">installation instructions</link>.
	    </p>
    </answer>
</faq>
<faq>
    <question>When I try to run Batik it results in a
    NoSuchMethodException.  What is the problem?</question>
    <answer>
        <p>There is certainly something wrong with your
        classpath. Clear your CLASSPATH environment variable and be
        sure to remove all the libraries which use the W3C's DOM
        bindings from <code>jre/lib/ext</code>before running any of
        the Batik's applications.</p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>When I change the document in Java it doesn't update the
    display, even if I call repaint?</question>
    <answer>
    <p>There are two common causes for this.  The first is that
    the JSVGCanvas doesn't know it's a dynamic document.  Normally
    Batik detects this by looking for script elements but when you
    modify the document from Java it can't tell.  So call
    JSVGCanvas.setDocumentState(JSVGCanvas.ALWAYS_DYNAMIC) before
    loading the document (with setURI, setDocument, setSVGDocument etc.).</p>
    <p>The second common reason is that the changes aren't made in
    the UpdateManager's thread.  You can run code in the UpdateManager's
    thread with the following:
    </p>
    <code>UpdateManager um = JSVGCanvas.getUpdateManager();</code>
    <code>um.getUpdateRunnableQueue().invokeLater(Runnable);</code>
    <p><strong>NOTE:</strong> The update manager only becomes
    available after the first rendering completes.  You can
    be notified when this happens by registering a 
    GVTTreeRendererListener.
    </p>
    </answer>
</faq>
  <faq>
    <question>When I change the document in Java it only updates if I
              move the mouse over the canvas?</question>
    <answer>
      <p>The most common causes for this, is that the changes are not made in
      the UpdateManager's thread.  See previous FAQ for example code to
      run code in the Update Manager's thread.  Moving the mouse works
      because it delivers the mouse move events in the update thread,
      and after a runnable completes in the Update Manager's thread it
      checks if the canvas needs repainting.</p>
    </answer>
  </faq>
<faq>
    <question>When I create new SVG elements or modify some 
    SVG attributes through the DOM API, from ECMA Script,
    nothing happens, the changes are not rendered, why not?</question>

    <answer>
    <p>A common problem is that script contain the wrong DOM calls
    to create elements or modify attributes. </p>

    <p>SVG elements need to be 
    created in the SVG namespace. For example, to create a 
    <code>&lt;rect&gt;</code> element, you should use 
    <code>document.createElementNS(svgNS, "rect")</code>, (where 
    <code>svgNS</code> is equals to <code>"http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"</code>),
    which appropriately creates the <code>&lt;rect&gt;</code> element in the
    SVG namespace. A call to <code>document.createElement("rect")</code> 
    creates an element with the tag <code>rect</code> but which does not 
    belong to the  SVG namespace. As such, it is ignored by Batik.</p>
    <p>Most SVG attributes belong to what is called the 'per element type 
    partition namespace' (see the 
    <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names">Namespaces in
    XML</link> specification). The appropriate way to set attributes on
    an SVG element is a call to <code>setAttributeNS</code> with a namespace
    value of <code>null</code>, for example: <code>elt.setAttributeNS(null, 
    "width", "40")</code>.  In the Batik SVG DOM implementation, you can 
    also use a call to <code>setAttribute</code> and you can write 
    <code>elt.setAttribute("width", "40")</code>. However, it is important
    to know that some implementations make a difference between 
    <code>setAttribute(x, y)</code> and 
    <code>setAttributeNS(null, x, y)</code>, so it is a better practice to use 
    <code>setAttributeNS</code> which is the only guaranteed interoperable 
    way of setting attributes in a namespace aware DOM implementation.</p>
    <p>Finally, for attributes which belong to a specific namespace, like the 
    the href attribute on the <code>&lt;image&gt;</code> element, you have to 
    use the <code>setAttributeNS</code> method with the XLink namespace. 
    For example, assuming <code>img</code> references an 
    <code>&lt;image&gt;</code> DOM <code>Element</code>, you can modify the 
    href as follows: <code>img.setAttributeNS(xlinkNS, "xlink:href", 
    "myImage.jpg")</code> where <code>xlinkNS</code> is equal to 
    <code>"http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"</code></p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>When I get the UpdateManager from the canvas sometimes
    it is null, why?</question>
    <answer>
    <p>The JSVGCanvs is highly asynchronous so when you call
    setURI, setDocument or setSVGDocument they return essentially 
    immediately. Behind the scenes the Canvas creates the rendering 
    tree and does a first rendering after running 'onload' scripts. 
    Only after this first rendering does the UpdateManger become
    available.
    </p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>Why do I have to go through the UpdateManager to
    run my code? Can't you just synchronize the DOM?</question>
    <answer>
    <p>It would be possible to synchronize individual calls to
    the DOM, however in general this is almost useless for the
    way DOM works.  For example creating a single rectangle
    element takes approximately 6 individual DOM calls.  So
    higher level synchronization is needed.
    </p>
    <p>The use of a Runnable is a common way of accomplishing
    synchronization for a block of code. This is essentially the
    approach that Swing takes (all Swing modification should take
    place in the Swing thread).  It was considered to use the Swing
    event thread, but this would lock the user interface while scripts
    were working.
    </p>
    </answer>
</faq>


<faq>
    <question>
    I can use the Batik extension tags with the source distribution
    but not with the binary distribution.  What am I missing?
    </question>
    <answer>
    	<p> When running from the <link
    	href="install.html#distributions">source distribution</link>
    	you automatically get the service provider entries for the
    	Batik extension tags (regularPolygon, and star for example).
    	We chose not to include these by default in the <link
    	href="install.html#distributions">binary distribution</link>
    	for the Batik applications.
    	</p>
    	<p> There is a subdirectory called 'extensions' that has jar files
    	that enable the extended elements from Batik.  </p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>
    Why do I get red circles when I view the samples/extensions files?
    </question>
    <answer><p>
    You are using the <link href="install.html#distributions">binary 
    distribution</link>. This distribution does not include support for 
    our example extensions (they are just examples and other people can 
    do more sophisticated things).
    </p>
    
    <p>
    If you want to view these examples you need to use the extension
    enabled versions of the applications in the 'extensions' subdirectory.
    </p></answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>
        I am modifying the DOM after displaying it in the JSVGCanvas,
        but my changes aren't shown (even if I call repaint).
    </question>

    <answer>
        <p>For efficiency if Batik Loads a static document it doesn't
        setup all the dynamic support.  Batik normally decides a
        document is not dynamic by checking if it contains any
        'script' elements.  However if your Java Application is
        modifying the DOM directly there may be no script elements.
        In this case you need to tell Batik to setup dynamic
        support anyways.</p>

        <p>The easiest way to do this is to call
        org.apache.batik.swing.JSVGCanvas.setDocumentState() with the
        constant JSVGCanvas.ALWAYS_DYNAMIC.</p>
    </answer>
</faq>
<faq>
    <question>
    I am trying to use Batik and FOP together but Batik does not work and
    fails on the <code>org.w3c.xxx packages</code>. What is happening?
    </question>

    <answer>
        <p>Both FOP and Batik use the <code>org.w3c.xxx
        packages</code>.  Depending on the version of FOP and Batik,
        Batik has been using a version of these packages which is more
        recent than the one in the w3c.jar file FOP uses. However, if
        the <code>w3c.jar</code>, file which comes with the FOP
        distribution is loaded before the Batik jar files, then, the
        version coming with FOP takes precedence (i.e., that is the
        version the Java Virtual Machine loads). Because that version
        is incompatible with Batik, you get a failure.</p>

        <p>The solution is to either repackage the
        <code>w3c.jar</code> file with the classes in the Batik
        distribution (you will need the Batik source distrib to do
        that), or you will need to make sure the Batik jars are loaded
        before the <code>w3c.jar</code>, for example by putting them
        before the <code>w3c.jar</code> file in your classpath. If you
        are copying your jar files to <code>..jre/lib/ext</code>, you
        can simply remove the FOP <code>w3c.jar</code> file from that
        directory.</p>
    </answer>
</faq>
<faq>
    <question>
    How do I checkout the latest CVS version of Batik?
    </question> 
    <answer>
      <p>You just have to follow the instructions posted on the
      <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cvs.html">XML Apache CVS page</link>.
      </p>
    </answer>
</faq>
<faq>
    <question>
    I'm using Mac OS X, and some of the SVG files I view are messed up (things
    appear clipped or out of place).  What do I need to do to fix this?
    </question> 
    <answer>
      <p>As of Mac OS X release 10.1.1 there still appear to be
      problems in the Apple implementation of the Java 2D API's. The
      true source of these problems and/or work arounds have yet to be
      identified (although the problems appear to be closely tied to a
      'gstack underflow' error messages from the Apple JVM). We are
      interested in finding the source of these problems and
      reasonable work arounds, so if you know what causes these errors
      the Batik team would be very interested in hearing from you
      (either directly or through the user/developer mailing lists).
      </p>

      <p>Other things to be aware of on Mac OS X, due to fixes for
      other problems with Java 2D under Mac OS X, you may find that
      some filtering operations take significantly more memory than on
      other platforms.  This will be especially true for deeply nested
      filter trees (where the result of one filtering operation is
      filtered by another filtering operation).</p>

      <p>Finally a few hints on avoiding problems under Mac OS X. The
      bugs seems to be triggered by filters (I've never seen a pure
      raster SVG document 'mess up').  The use of the 'filterRes'
      attribute on the 'filter' element seems especially problematic.
      The bug isn't 100% reproducible, so while some content has the
      problem a lot if you play with the document enough it will often
      'fix' it's self for a while, then after a while it will go back
      to being broken (this makes me think the problem may be some
      sort of race condition in the JVM).</p>
    </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
    <question>
    I cannot run the Batik demo on Mac OS X (10.1.1). The Batik splash screen hangs.
    What is happening?
    </question>
    <answer>
    <p>The Batik <link href="http://xml.apache.org/batik/batikDemo.html">demo</link> uses Java Web Start. Java Web Start (under the Applications/Utilities
    folder), lets you start a Java application from a web browser. You can see the debug
    traces by enabling the Java console for Java Web Start. If you do, you will see that
    there is a <code>java.lang.NoSuchMethodError</code> exception thrown.</p>
    <p>This is happening because the Java Web Start jar file (<code>javaws.jar in /Applications/Utilities/Java Web Start/Content/MacOS)</code>
    contains an older version of the DOM bindings.</p>
    <p>One work around is to manually patch the javaws.jar file to remove the DOM bindings
    so that they do not take precedence over the Batik ones.</p>
    </answer>
</faq>
</faqs>
