<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<!-- ========================================================================= -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Apache Software Foundation. All rights reserved.        -->
<!--                                                                           -->
<!-- This software is published under the terms of the Apache Software License -->
<!-- version 1.1, a copy of which has been included with this distribution in  -->
<!-- the LICENSE file.                                                         -->
<!-- ========================================================================= -->

<!-- ========================================================================= -->
<!-- author vincent.hardy@eng.sun.com                                          -->
<!-- version $Id$ -->
<!-- ========================================================================= -->
<document>
    <header>
        <title>Batik SVG Toolkit</title>
        <subtitle>SVG Tools in Java</subtitle>
        <authors>
            <person name="Vincent Hardy" email="vincent.hardy@eng.sun.com"/>
            <person name="Thierry Kormann" email="tkormann@apache.org"/>
            <person name="Stephane Hillion" email="stephane@hillion.org"/>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>
        <s1 title="Batik Overview">

        <p>
        Batik is a Java based toolkit for applications which
        images in the <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/">Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG)</link> format for
        various purposes, such as viewing, generation or manipulation.
        </p>
        <p>
        The project's ambition is to give developers a set of core modules which can be used together 
        or individually to support specific SVG solutions. Examples of modules are SVG parsers, SVG 
        generators and SVG DOM implementations. Even though the goal of the project is to provide a set 
        of core modules, one of the deliveries is a full fledged SVG Viewer implementation which 
        validates the various modules and their inter-operability. 
        </p>

        </s1>

        <s1 title="Applications of Batik">
        <p>
        With Batik, you can view SVG documents on all platforms where
        Java is available. You can also use the various Batik modules to
        generate, manipulate, transcode and search SVG images in your 
        applications.
        </p>
        <p>
        Batik makes it easy for Java based applications to deal with SVG
        contents. For example, using Batik's SVG generator, a Java application
        can very easily export its graphics in the SVG format. Using 
        Batik's SVG processor and viewer, an application can very easily
        integrate SVG viewing capabilities. Another possibilities is to
        use Batik's modules to convert SVG to various formats, such as 
        raster images (JPEG or PNG).
        </p>
        <p>
        Batik provides core components for handling and processing SVG
        files.
        </p>
         </s1>

        <s1 title="Batik Limitations">

        <p>
        At this time, Batik does not support all of the SVG features. It 
        provides a good support for all the SVG static features, supports
        linking, and has some scripting support, even though dynamic 
        modification of SVG documents is not yet available. 
        </p>
        <p>
        You will find a detailed description of the set of SVG features
        Batik supports on the 
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/xml-batik/status.xml">Status</link>
        page.
        </p>
        </s1>

        <s1 title="SVG 1.0 Beta Support">
        <p>
        Scalable Vector Graphics, SVG, is a <link href="http://www.w3.org">W3C</link>
        Candidate Recommendation. It defines an XML grammar for rich 2D graphics
        which includes features such as transparency, arbitrary geometry, filter
        effects (shadows, lighting effects, etc...), scripting and animation.
        </p>
        <p>
        The SVG specification can be found on the 
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/">W3C site</link>.
        </p>
         </s1>
 
        <s1 title="Batik Download">
        <p>
        You can get Batik on the 
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/xml-batik/download/">download page</link>.
        </p>
        <note>
        All other libraries needed by Batik are included in the distribution.
        After you downloaded Batik, you will not need anything else.
        </note>
        </s1>

        <s1 title="Contributions To The Batik Project">
        <p>
        The Batik Project is an open volunteer project based on the spirit of the
        <link href="http://www.apache.org">Apache Software Foundation</link> (ASF).
        This means that there are lots of ways to contribute to the project, either
        with direct participation (coding, documenting, answering questions,
        proposing ideas, reporting bugs, suggesting bug-fixes, etc..) or by resource
        donation (publicity, hardware, software, conference
        presentations, speeches, etc...).
        </p>
        <p>
        For direct participation, we suggest you to subscribe to the
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">Batik mailing list</link>
        (follow the link for information on how to subscribe and to access the mail
        list archives), to checkout the <link href="http://xml.apache.org/websrc/index.cgi/xml-batik/">latest code</link>.
        </p>
        </s1>
    </body>
</document>
