<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">



<!-- I left this here so that you have a view of the structure of the thing
     feel free to add as you go -->




<document>
 <header>
  <title>Apache Batik</title>
  <subtitle>SVG Toolkit</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
 <s1 title="What is it?">

  <p>
   Cocoon is a 100% pure
   Java publishing framework that relies on new W3C
   technologies (such as DOM, XML, and XSL) to provide web content.
  </p>

  <p>
   The Cocoon project aims to change the way web information is created,
   rendered and served. This new paradigm is based on fact that document content, style and
   logic are often created by different individuals or working groups. Cocoon aims to a
   complete separation of the three layers, allowing the three layers to be independently
   designed, created and managed, reducing management overhead, increasing work reuse and
   reducing time to market.
  </p>

  <p>
   Read the <connect href="technologies.xml">Introduction on Cocoon
   technologies</connect> white paper to find out more on the subject.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="What does it do?">
  <p>
   Web content generation is mostly based on HTML, but HTML doesn't separate
   the information from its presentation, mixing formatting tags, descriptive tags and
   programmable logic (both on server side and client side). Cocoon changes this view
   allowing content, logic and style on different XML files and uses XSL transformation
   capabilities to merge them.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="What does it change for me?">
  <p>
   Even if the most common use of Cocoon is the automatic creation of HTML
   through the processing of statically or dynamically generated XML files, Cocoon is also
   able to perform more sophisticated formatting, such as XSL:FO rendering on PDF,
   client-depending transformations such as WML formatting for WAP-enabled
   devices or direct XML serving to XML and XSL aware clients.
  </p>

  <p>
   The Cocoon model allows web sites to be highly structured and
   well designed, reducing duplication efforts and site management costs by
   allowing different presentations of the same data depending on the requesting
   client (HTML clients, PDF clients, WML clients) and separating on different <em>contexts</em>
   different requirements, skills and capacities. Cocoon allows a better human
   resource management by giving to each individual its job and reducing to a
   minimum the cross-talks between different working contexts.
  </p>

  <p>
   To do this, the Cocoon model divides the development of web content in three
   separate levels:
  </p>

  <dl>
    <dt>XML creation</dt>
    <dd>the XML file is created by the <em>content owners</em>. They do not
     require specific knowledge on how the XML content is further processed rather than the
     particular chosen DTD/namespace. This layer is always performed by humans directly
     through normal text editors or XML-aware tools/editors.</dd>
    <dt>XML processing</dt>
    <dd>the requested XML file is processed and the logic contained in its
     logicsheet is applied. Unlike other dynamic content generators, the logic
     is separated from the content file.</dd>
    <dt>XSL rendering</dt>
    <dd>the created document is then rendered by applying an XSL
     stylesheet to it and formatting it to the specified resource type
     (HTML, PDF, XML, WML, XHTML)</dd>
  </dl>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Are there any known problems?">
  <p>
   The biggest known problem in this framework is the lack of XML/XSL
   knowledge, being relatively new formats. We do believe, though, that this publishing
   framework will be a winner in web sites of medium to high complexity and will lead the
   transition from an HTML-oriented to a XML-oriented web publishing model, still allowing the
   use of existing client technologies as well as supporting new types of clients
   (such as WAP-aware ultra thin clients like cell phones or PDAs).
  </p>
  <p>
   Even if considered heavy and hype overloaded, the XML/XSL pair will do
   magic once its public knowledge receives the spread it deserves. This project wants to be
   a small step in this direction, helping people to learn this technology and to focus on
   what they need with examples, tutorial and source code and a real-life system
   carefully designed with portability, modularity and real-life usage in
   mind.
  </p>
  <p>
   The main concern remains processing complexity: the kind of operations required
   to process the document layers are complex and not designed for real-time
   operation on the server side. For this reason, Cocoon is designed to be a page compiler for dynamic pages,
   trying to hardcode, whenever possible, those layers in precompiled binary
   code coupled with an adaptive and memory-wise cache system for both static and
   dynamic pages. Most of the development effort is focused on performance
   improvement of both processing subsystems as well as the creation and testing
   of special cache systems.
  </p>
  <p>
   Another problem is the intrinsic impossibility of page-compiling all the three
   processing layers, due to the post-processing requirements of XSL styling. This
   problem will be solved (hopefully!) with the availability of XSL-enabled
   web browsers since the XSL rendering would be then
   performed on client side reducing the server work.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Are there books that cover this stuff?">
  <p>
   Yes, even if XML publishing is a brand new area, the incredible acceptance
   of these technologies urged editors to provide books that covered the subject.
   While many books that cover XML exist, one of them dedicates an entire chapter
   to XML publishing frameworks and Cocoon in particular and that chapter
   was made available free of charge 
   <link href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/javaxml/chapter/ch09.html">here</link>.
   Our greatful thanks go to both O'Reilly and Brett McLaughlin for this.
  </p>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="Where do I get it?">
  <p>
   The official distribution site is <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/dist/">here</link>.
  </p>
  <note>
   Since Cocoon requires many different packages to work (Xerces, Xalan, FOP, etc...)
   but sometimes there are small incompatibilities between them that make the
   installation harder, we decided to help you by placing all the required
   binary libraries inside the Cocoon distribution. So, after you
   downloaded the latest Cocoon distribution, <strong>you don't need anything else</strong>.
  </note>
  <p>
   But, if you want, you can find unofficial RPM packages <link href="http://grapeape.codingapes.com/xml.xml">here</link>.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="How do I Contribute?">
  <p>
   The Cocoon Project is an open volunteer project based on the spirit of the
   <link href="http://www.apache.org">Apache Software Foundation</link> (ASF).
   This means that there are lots of ways to contribute to the project, either
   with direct participation (coding, documenting, answering questions,
   proposing ideas, reporting bugs, suggesting bug-fixes, etc..) or by resource
   donation (money, time, publicity, hardware, software, conference
   presentations, speeches, etc...).
  </p>
  <p>
   For direct participation, we suggest you to subscribe to the
   <link href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">Cocoon mail lists</link>
   (follow the link for information on how to subscribe and to access the mail
   list archives), to checkout the <link href="http://xml.apache.org/websrc/cvsweb.cgi/xml-cocoon/">
   latest and greatest code</link> (which you found in the xml-cocoon module in
   the xml.apache.org CVS code repository, or from the
   <link href="http://xml.apache.org/from-cvs/xml-cocoon/">CVS snapshots</link>),
   control the <connect href="../todo.xml">todo</connect>
   list and jump in. Document writers are usually the most wanted people so if
   you like to help but you're not familiar with technical details, don't worry:
   we have work for you.
  </p>
  <p>
   For money funding in particular, the Cocoon Project and the ASF in general
   is closely collaborating with the <link href="http://www.sourcexchange.com">Collab.net
   SourceXchange</link> program that will provide a legal, solid and well
   established resource for money collecting to fund direct software production
   under the open source flag. Please, feel free to contact directly Cocoon's
   main architect and project creator <link href="mailto:stefano@apache.org">Stefano
   Mazzocchi</link> or the ASF President and Collab.net co-founder <link href="mailto:brian@collab.net">Brian
   Behlendorf</link> for more information on how to contribute directly to the
   advancement of this project.
  </p>
  <p>
   Anyway, a great way of contributing back to the project is to
   allow others to know about it so that the word spreads and others may wish to
   contribute, so, please, help us by placing the cocoon logo somewhere in your
   site to indicate that you are using and supporting the Cocoon Project.
  </p>

  <p>
   Thank you very much.
  </p>
 </s1>
 </body>
</document>
