<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<!--

   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.

-->

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- author stephane@hillion.org                                            -->
<!-- version $Id$    -->
<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<document>
    <header>
        <title>Contributors</title>
        <subtitle>Batik People</subtitle>
        <authors>
            <person name="Stephane Hillion" email="stephane@hillion.org"/>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>
      <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p>
      This page contains informations about the current Batik developers and
      the features they are working on at the moment.
      </p>
      </s1>

      <anchor id="BatikCommitters" />
      <s1 title="Batik Committers">
      <p>
      This section lists all the Batik committers.
      </p>
      <p>
      The following people are active Batik developers:
      </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>Thomas DeWeese (TD)</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:Thomas.DeWeese@Kodak.com">Thomas.DeWeese@Kodak.com</link> <br />
          <em>
          Thomas DeWeese is a Senior Software Engineer at Eastman Kodak Company,
          in Rochester New York where he has worked for the Image Science
          Division's, image application development group since 1994.  Thomas
          has made contributions to the imaging portions of the Java2D API,
          and was a major contributor to the Java Advanced Image API (version
          1.0).  Since then he has participated in the Jini Printing Working
          group and has recently become a member of Kodak's SVG Working Group
          team.
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Vincent Hardy (VH)</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:vincent.hardy@eng.sun.com">vincent.hardy@eng.sun.com</link><br />
          <em>Vincent is one of the founders of the SVG Batik project at Apache and the Batik 
          team contact. He is a Senior Staff Engineer at Sun Microsystems Inc., where he 
          is part of the XML technology center.
          Vincent represents Sun in the W3C's SVG Working Group and is currently a W3C fellow in
          the W3C office in Sophia Antipolis, France.
          Vincent is the author of papers and a book on the Java 2D API.</em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Stephane Hillion (SH)</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:shillion@ilog.fr">shillion@ilog.fr</link><br />
          <em>
          Stephane is a software engineer at the Koala project, part of
          the ILOG's visualization R&amp;D team, located in Sophia-Antipolis,
          France. His main interests are in programming languages and web
          standards. He wrote the Apache Batik's DOM, CSS and Swing modules.
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Christophe Jolif (CJ)</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:cjolif@ilog.fr">cjolif@ilog.fr</link><br />
          <em>
          Christophe Jolif is a Software Architect mainly working on the ILOG
          JViews Component Suite, the ILOG Java visualization framework. He has
          been working for ILOG since 1997, and is representing the company at the
          Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) W3C Working Group since 1999. He has 
          implemented the SVG import and export features in ILOG JViews and is now
          also working on the SVG Batik project at Apache.
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Thierry Kormann (TK)</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:tkormann@ilog.fr">tkormann@ilog.fr</link> <br />
          <em>

Thierry is a software engineer, at the Koala project of ILOG located at
Sophia-Antipolis, France and a member of the SVG working group. Thierry has
contributed to most of the Koala's projects involving Java and XML. Since
then, he co-founded the Apache Batik project. His daytime job is focused on
Graphics and XML related technologies. Prior to joining ILOG, Thierry worked
as a software engineer for Bull.</em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Nicolas Socheleau</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:nicolas.socheleau@bitflash.com">nicolas.socheleau@bitflash.com</link> <br />
          <em>
Nicolas Socheleau is a software engineer at BitFlash Inc, Ottawa, Canada 
where he worked on different SVG related projects. He joined the Batik 
team in June 2002. His interests include XML technologies and Graphics. He
contributed some text functionnalities and SVG DOM interface implementations.
</em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

        </dl>

        <p>
        The following people are some of the Batik project founders and
        helped define and implement the initial Batik architecture:
        </p>

        <dl>
          <dt>Bill Haneman</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:bill.haneman@ireland.sun.com">bill.haneman@ireland.sun.com</link><br />
          <em>
          Bill Haneman works for Sun Microsystems' Desktop Enabling Middleware
          group in Dublin, Ireland, and implemented much of the Batik's text
          support (though not SVG Fonts, thanks Bella, Dean, and David!).  He is
          also technical lead for the Gnome Accessibility Project
          (http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gap), an open project to provide
          an accessibility framework for linux and Solaris(TM) desktops.  A
          twenty-year veteran of scientific programming and application
          development, he is a US expatriate who plays traditional Irish music
          on the uilleann pipes. 
          </em> 
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Dean Jackson</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:dean.jackson@cmis.csiro.au">dean.jackson@cmis.csiro.au</link><br />
          <em>
          Dean is employed by CSIRO Australia and is currently working at
          the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) full time on SVG. He is a member
          of the W3C's SVG working group, and was a developer
          of the CSIRO SVG Toolkit, one of the first and most complete open source
          SVG libraries. 
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>

          <dt>Emmanuel Tissandier</dt><dd><br />
          <link href="mailto:tissandi@ilog.fr">tissandi@ilog.fr</link><br />
          <em>
          Emmanuel Tissandier has been working for 10 years as a software engineer
          in object oriented environments. He started with the development of CASE
          tools at Rank Xerox and joined the visualization R&amp;D team of ILOG in
          1995. Since 1997, he has been the R&amp;D Project Manager for the ILOG
          JViews Component Suite, a product for delivering two-dimensional
          structured graphics, cartography, diagrams, and Gantt charts in Java.  
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <p>
        Bella Robinson implemented the SVG fonts support in Batik:
        </p>
        <dl>
        <dt>Bella Robinson</dt><dd><br />
        <link href="mailto:bella.robinson@cmis.csiro.au">Bella Robinson</link>
          <em>
          Bella is a Software Engineer working for CSIRO Australia. She was one
          of the main developers of the CSIRO SVG Toolkit and has also been working
          on a Pocket SVG Viewer for handheld devices. Her interests include 
          graphics and XML programming.
          </em>
          <br /><br />
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <p>
        In addition, <link href="mailto:James.Davidson@eng.sun.com">James Davidson</link>
        and <link href="mailto:stefano@apache.org">Stefano Mazzochi</link> , two Apache veterans who helped the
        Batik team start the project at Apache, also have commit access to the SVN repository.
        </p>        
      </s1>

      <anchor id="BatikContributors" />
      <s1 title="Batik Contributors">
      <p>
      The following people have contributed to Batik:
      </p>
        <ul>
          <li><link href="mailto:carnold@houston.rr.com">Curt Arnold</link> - Contributed many bug reports and fixes</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:r_diblasi@hotmail.com">Robert A. DiBlasi</link> - Contributed a lot of feedback on the 
            Batik documentation and suggestions on how to improve it</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:Paul_Evenblij@nl.compuware.com">Paul Evenblij</link> - Contributed an improvement to 
            the way images are handled by the SVGGraphics2D component. Also contributed bug fixes on the SVGGraphics2D
            component. </li>
          <li><link href="mailto:pier.fumagalli@eng.sun.com">Pier Fumagalli</link>- is helping us with the Batik web site and
              mailing lists.</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:Christophe.Held@sophia.inria.fr">Christophe Held</link> - Contributed a math formula in SVG 
              generated from MathML. </li>
          <li><link href="mailto:keiron@aftexsw.com">Keiron Liddle</link> - A <link href="http://xmlgraphics.apache.org/fop/">FOP</link>
              member who is working on an SVG to PDF transcoder that will be part of FOP but that will work in 
              the Batik infrastructure</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:john.morrison@uk.experian.com">John Morrison</link> - Contributed a set of XSL stylesheets
              to generate SVG charts, such as line graphs, bar charts or pie charts</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:neumann@karto.baug.ethz.ch">Andreas Neumann</link> - Contributed two SVG maps which 
              <link href="bert@w3.org">Bert Bos</link> has internationalized (adding an English version to the original
              German text).</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:luano@asd.ie">Luan O'Carroll</link> - Contributed the WMF transcoder.</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:spei@cs.uiowa.edu">Sheng Pei</link> - Contributed on filters and the Regard tool.</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:neeme.praks@one.ee">Neeme Praks</link> - Contributed patches, feedback and scripts for
            building charts from John Morrisson's XSL stylesheets</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:ruini@iki.fi">Henri Ruini</link> - Contributed to a rewrite of the rasterizer application. </li>
          <li><link href="mailto:david@steadystate.co.uk">David Schweinsberg</link> - Contributed the True Type Font to 
              SVG Font converter</li>
          <li><link href="mailto:natalian@cs.brown.edu">Nicholas Talian</link> - Contributed on gradients.</li>
        </ul>
      </s1>

      <s1 title="Areas of Expertise">
        <p>
        The following table summarizes the areas of expertise of each active
        committer. It allows better coordination of both internal and
        external development efforts.
        </p>

        <table>
          <tr>
            <th/><th>TD</th><th>VH</th><th>SH</th><th>CJ</th><th>TK</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Team Contact</td>
            <td/><td>X</td><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>SMIL Animation</td>
            <td/><td/><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Bridge</td>
            <td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>CSS</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Documentation</td>
            <td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>SVG DOM</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>GVT Core</td>
            <td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td/><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>GVT Filters</td>
            <td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>GVT Renderer</td>
            <td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>GVT Text</td>
            <td>X</td><td/><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>SVGGraphics2D</td>
            <td/><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Micro Parsers</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td/><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Scripting</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Swing Components</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Rasterizer</td>
            <td/><td/><td/><td/><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Browser</td>
            <td/><td/><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Test</td>
            <td/><td>X</td><td/><td/><td/>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </s1>
    </body>
</document>
